Women's Development Corporation Records, 1979-2015
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
JWomen's Development Corporation Records, 1979-2015
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2016-012
8.5 Cubic Feet
The Women’s Development Corporation (WDC) is a Rhode Island based housing developer and non-profit founded by a group of architects, designers, community planners, and historic preservation professionals. These records document select activities of the WDC from 1979-2015.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Women’s Development Corporation Records were donated to Special Collections in 2016.
Historical Note
The Women’s Development Corporation (WDC) is a non-profit housing developer in Rhode Island. The WDC was founded in 1979 by a group of architects, designers, community planners, and historic preservation professionals. The original board included Alma Green (President, 1979-2012), Susan Aitcheson (co-founder, Vice President 1979-2012, and President from 2012-2015), Myrna Breitbart, Joan Forrester Sprague, and Kathleen McDonald. The WDC designs, develops, constructs, and manages sustainable housing for low and moderate income families, individuals with special needs, and elderly residents. Between 1979 and 2016, the WDC had developed over 1600 housing units.
Additional sources: http://www.wdchoc.org/about-wdc http://www.wdchoc.org/FAQ
Scope and Content
These records document select activities of the Women's Development Corporation (WDC) of Rhode Island from 1979-2015. Materials include professional correspondence from WDC staff to peers, funding agencies, politicians, and clients; commendations received by the WDC; research notes and reports; administrative records, including meeting minutes and bylaws; public relations materials; press coverage by and about the WDC; project documentation, including design sketches, presentation drawings, photographs, and planning materials; audio-visual recordings; electronic records on DVD; and furniture models used in the participatory design planning process.
Arrangement
This collection was arranged with respect to the original order and the Shephered/Lowell Standard Series and Subseries for Architeture and Landscape Design. The collection reflects the following series and subseries:
Series I: Photographs
Series II: Professional Papers
Subseries A: Correspondence related to the profession
Subseries B: Awards, certificates
Subseries C: Research Notes and Data Collection
Subseries D: Files, articles, clipping, materials
Subseries E: Women's School of Planning and Architecture
Series III: OFfice Records
Subseries A: Administrative articles, bylaws, meetings
Subseries B: Housing Planning Group Meetings, 1980
Subseries C: Public Relations Activity
Subseries D: Published Materials Subseries E: Exercises and analysis
Series IV: Project Records
Series V: Participatory Design Workshop, 1989
Series VI: Aduiovisual and Electronic Media Series VII: Exhibits and Artifacts
Index Terms
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); History of Women in Architecture; Women architects -- Rhode Island; Women's Development Corporation (R. I.)
Contents List
- SERIES I: Photographs
  Contains photographs of Susan Aitcheson’s retirement, 2015.
  - Susan Aitcheson retires, 2015 (Box-folder 1:1)
- SERIES II: Professional Papers
  The Professional Papers series consists of material relating WDC’s great effort to gather funding and support from several organizations and institutions to fund and subsidize housing for low income women and families. This is supported by correspondence, research notes, reference files related to both the profession and the role of women in architecture. Particular attention was given to the WSPA - Women’s School of Planning and Architecture, with related correspondence, publicity, awards.
  - SUBSERIES A: Correspondence related to the profession
    - Proposal 1979 + Accompanying Correspondence (Box-folder 1:2)
    - EDA - Economic Development Administration (January 1979) (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Becky Peterson (1979) to S. Aitcheson, J. Sprague, M. Kennedy (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Congressman Fernand Germaine (January 1979 - April 1984) (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Secretary Simons (July 1980) (Box-folder 1:6)
    - H.U.D. Regional (August-September 1980) (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Congresswoman Claudine Schneider (November 1980 - August 1981) (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Senator John Chafee (July 1981 - January 1982) (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Ralph Pari - (June 1983) (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Elizabeth Earls - Community Mental Health Centers - (September 1993) (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Deborah Pond - Women's Housing & Economic Development Corporation-(December 1998) (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Don Roberts (April 1999) (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Myrna Breitbart (Box-folder 1:14-22)
    - Jennifer Bramley - (August 2004) (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Correspondence Andrea Merrett (March - April 2012) (Box-folder 1:24)
  - SUBSERIES B: Awards, certificates
    - Susan Aitcheson's License (Box-folder 1:25)
    - APA Awards & Proposal, 1980 (Box-folder 1:26-29)
  - SUBSERIES C: Research Notes and Data Collection
    - Breitbart Questionnaire & Answers (Box-folder 1:30)
    - Breitbart - Some Research Notes (Box-folder 1:31)
    - Information Emily Card - HUD (Box-folder 1:32)
    - Berlin Conference, 1981-06-24 (Box-folder 1:33)
    - Housing Group Design Exercises and Questionnaires (Box-folder 1:34-35)
    - Tenant Selection (Box-folder 1:36)
    - Outline of Development process, 1981 (Box-folder 1:37)
  - SUBSERIES D: Files, articles, clipping, materials
    - Article "Women's school ends successful summer", 1975-10 (Box-folder 1:38)
    - Spokeswoman - Magazine Volume 10, Number 5, 1980-05 (Box-folder 1:39)
    - “Women Consumers, Women Professionals, 1980 (Box-folder 1:40)
    - "Making it ourselves" (Box-folder 1:41)
    - "Designing for the Messiness of Life", 1981-02 (Box-folder 1:42)
    - "Sisterhood is braced for the Reaganauts", 1981-05 (Box-folder 1:43)
    - "What an architect does - and doesn't do", 1986-08 (Box-folder 1:44)
    - Journal of Housing & Community Development (Box-folder 1:45)
    - Progressive Architecture - Women in Architecture: Leveling the Playing Field, 1995-11 (Box-folder 1:46)
    - Sophia Smith Collection - Printed Webpage Search, 2010 (Box-folder 1:47)
    - "Cohousing" book with note (Box-folder 1:48)
    - Impacts Press (Box-folder 1:58)
  - SUBSERIES E: Women's School of Planning and Architecture
    - WSPA News Report, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1:49)
    - Correspondence: Linda Moody, 1980-06 (Box-folder 1:50)
    - Correspondence: Carol Randles, 1980-07 (Box-folder 1:51)
    - Reference Files: WSPA, 1980 (Box-folder 1:52)
    - WSPA, 1980 (Box-folder 1:53-54)
    - Reference Files: Conference National Symposium Women, 1981 (Box-folder 1:56)
    - WSPA Clipping: Kathleen McDonald's Information (Box-folder 1:57)
- SERIES III: Office Records
  - SUBSERIES A: Administrative articles, bylaws, meetings
    - First Meeting in RI to Discuss Concepts, 1978-11 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - CSA Recommendation, 1979-02 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Documents, 1979 (Box-folder 2:3-17)
    - WDC Economic Development: An Affirmative Action Community Outreach Program, 1979-04 (Box-folder 2:18)
    - A Synopsis of Villa Excelsior (Box-folder 2:19)
    - WDC Program & Description, 1980-06 (Box-folder 2:20)
    - Final Report to TAP (Box-folder 2:21)
    - Proposed Mawney Street Cooperative (Box-folder 2:22)
    - Housing with Economic Development Description (Box-folder 2:23)
    - Vol II - Section V - Implementation Feasibility (Box-folder 2:24)
  - SUBSERIES B: Housing Planning Group Meetings, 1980
    - Housing Planning Meetings - Notes, 1980 (Box-folder 2:25)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - March Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:26)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - April Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:27-28)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - May Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:29)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - Boston trip (Box-folder 2:30-38)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - June Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:39-41)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - July Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:42)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - August Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:43)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - September Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:44)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - October Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:45-46)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - November Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:47-50)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - December Meetings, 1980 (Box-folder 2:51)
    - Summary of Housing Meetings (Box-folder 2:52)
    - Transitional Housing Planning Group (Box-folder 2:53)
    - Original Housing Planning Attendance (Box-folder 2:54)
    - Spanish Meeting Announcement Original (Box-folder 2:55)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - January Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:56)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - February Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:57)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - March Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:58)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - April Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:59)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - May Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:60)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - June Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:61)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - August Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:62)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - October Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:63)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - November Meetings, 1981 (Box-folder 2:64)
    - Boards of Directors - March, 1982-03 (Box-folder 2:65)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - July Meetings, 1982 (Box-folder 2:66)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - August Meetings, 1982 (Box-folder 2:67)
    - Text from visit to Boston with Housing Groups (Box-folder 2:68)
    - Housing Planning Meetings - Attendance (Box-folder 2:69)
    - House Planning Meetings - September, 1982 (Box-folder 2:70)
  - SUBSERIES C: Public Relations Activity
    - Ads & Info Forms (Box-folder 3:1)
    - General Notebook: Flyers (Box-folder 3:2)
    - General Notebook: Flyers (Box-folder 3:3)
    - General Notebook: Flyers - Documentation related to flyers (Box-folder 3:4)
    - General Notebook: Outreach - October to December 1979 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - General Notebook: Outreach for intro MTG - November 28, 1979 - PaceSponsor (Box-folder 3:6)
    - General Notebook: Outreach for intro MTG -December 11th, 1980 (Box-folder 3:7)
    - General Notebook: Outreach January 1980 Presentation (Box-folder 3:8)
    - General Notebook: Outreach May 1980 (Box-folder 3:9)
    - General Notebook: Business Interests (Box-folder 3:10)
    - General Notebook: Introduction Meetings (Box-folder 3:11)
    - General Notebook: Sample Forms (Box-folder 3:12)
    - General Notebook: Building Maintenance (Box-folder 3:13)
    - General Notebook: Workshops sponsored by W.D.C. (Box-folder 3:14)
    - General Notebook: Senior Craft (Box-folder 3:15)
  - SUBSERIES D: Published Materials
    - "American University National Symposium", 1981-05 (Box-folder 3:30)
    - Magazine "Canadian Woman Studies Les Cahiers de la Femme", 1990 (Box-folder 3:31)
    - "Affordable - Housing Program launched", 1991-03 (Box-folder 3:32)
    - "A conversation with Alma Green", 1995-04 (Box-folder 3:33)
    - "Planning New Living Spaces for the Nontraditional Family", 1984-09 (Box-folder 3:34)
    - "City Group offers hope for families", 1992-06 (Box-folder 3:35)
    - "Bringing Life to West End", 1992-07 (Box-folder 3:36)
    - "Nonprofit Group well on its way to $3 million", 1992-01 (Box-folder 3:37)
    - "Quality housing for Women and Children" - Breitbart, 1990 (Box-folder 3:38)
    - "Female Solutions to Housing Need", 1990-11 (Box-folder 3:39)
    - "The Cork Examiner" articles, 1995-02 (Box-folder 3:40)
    - "A best practice toolkit for historic preservation" (Box-folder 3:41)
    - "Hope resides in a historic house", 1995-07 (Box-folder 3:42)
    - "The new Master Builders", 1998-07 (Box-folder 3:43)
    - "More than Housing" - Joan Sprague (Box-folder 3:44)
    - "Establishing Grounds" - Myrna Breitbart, 1995 (Box-folder 3:45)
    - Magazine "Architecture" - article photocopy, 1998-07 (Box-folder 3:46)
    - Magazine "Architecture", 1998-07 (Box-folder 3:47)
    - WDC History & Articles stapled (Box-folder 3:48)
    - "Aging in Place" (Box-folder 3:49)
    - "More than Shelter. A Manual on Transitional Housing" (Box-folder 3:50)
    - "List of WDC Publications" (Box-folder 3:51)
  - SUBSERIES E: Exercises and analysis
    - Design exercises (Box-folder 3:52)
    - Site selection (Box-folder 3:53)
    - Spanish Neighborhood Analysis (Box-folder 3:54)
    - Neighborhood Analysis (Box-folder 3:55)
- SERIES IV: Project Records
  - List of Properties owned by WDC (Box-folder 3:56)
  - Projects In Progress and Completed, 1998 (Box-folder 3:57)
  - Developments & Properties, 1999-02 (Box-folder 3:58)
  - Projects in progress & Projects Completed, 1999 (Box-folder 3:59)
  - WDC properties, 2003-06 (Box-folder 3:60)
  - Sketched Floorplans (Box-folder 3:61)
  - Drawings and Plans (Box-folder 3:62)
  - Rolled drawings and sketches (Box 4)
  - Fifteenth Anniversary Portfolio Records, 1994 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Project Portfolio: Planning, Designing and Building Homes for Families and Communities, 1980-1997 (Box-item 8:2)
    Scrapbook portfolio documenting selected housing projects and properties developed by WDC between 1980-1997. Entitled "Planning, Designing and Building Homes for Families and Communities," the portfolio explores the WDC's Participatory Planning Design exercises and prototype development from 1980-1982. Originally established for the WDC's fifteenth anniversary and expanded over time to document new projects.
- SERIES V: Participatory Design Workshop, 1980
  This series comprises conceptual sketches, fabric and paint swatches, and planning activities from the WDC's original 1980 participatory design workshop with low-income women. The series also includes prototype floorplans produced by Susan Aitcheson after the workshop.
  - Participatory Design Activities (Oversize 1)
  - Prototype Drawings (Oversize 2, Box-folder 3:62)
  - Fabric and paint swatch selections (Oversize 3)
- SERIES VI: Audiovisual and Electronic Media
  - Women's Development Corporation, Fall 1998 - Tapes 1,2,3 (Box-item 5:1)
    Footage shot for Dream Builders on Home & Garden Television. Betacam SP tape.
  - Women's Development Corporation, Fall 1998 - Tapes 4,5 (Box-item 5:2)
  - Audiocassette, "Tent City", 2 sides (Box-item 5:3)
  - Audiocassette, Side 1: "Vivia Victoria, 1st Nov 15, 1980" / Side 2: "Ann Kerry @ Villa Vicotira, Nov 15, 1980" (Box-item 5:4)
  - Audiocassette, Side 1: "Alma's interview, rodie, 8/2/8/81" / Side 2: "Christmas Party - Children Singing, 12/19/83" (Box-item 5:5)
  - Dream Builders - Women's Development Corp (Box-item 6:1)
    VHS tape
  - Susan Aitcheson Interview, 4-16-13 (Box-item 6:2)
    DVD-R, interview conducted by Andrea Merrett, Columbia University Archives
  - Home & Garden Network, WDC NAHB (Box-item 6:3)
    DVD-R
  - Women's Development Corporation (Box-item 6:4)
    DVD, Running Time 8 min 40 sec
  - WDC Archive: Photos, Posterboards, Powerpoint, 9.20.15 (Box-item 6:5)
    DVD+RW
  - WDC Archive (Box-item 6:6)
- SERIES VII: Exhibits and Artifacts
  - Furniture models (Box 7)
    Balsa wood and dyed cardboard furniture pieces used for participatory design activities.
  - Visual History and Timeline of WDC/HOC, 2015 (Oversize 1-12, Oversize 13-16)
    16 foamboard panels documenting the history of the Women's Development Corporation and its partner non-profit, the Housing Opportunities Corporation. The panels include newspaper clippings of opposition to WDC housing in its early years, a project breakdown by deecade, organizaitonal charts, lists of staff, and photographs of major projects and milestone events.